Guide to the Gene & Hedy Lee Chinese language newspapers & photographs, 1962-2010 (bulk 1976-1985) MS 556
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Gene & Hedy Lee Chinese community newspapers & photographs, and family records
1962-2010
1976-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Lee, Gene; Lee, Hedy, Mrs.
MS 556
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Newspaper issues of the Southwest Chinese Journal (cataloged separately), photographs submitted to the newspaper for publication purposes and a small amount of correspondence regarding the Lee Printing Company of Houston, Texas, owned by Gene and Hedy Lee. The newspapers and photographs reflect Chinese culture in Houston during the 1970s and 1980s, including family life, business activities, cultural arts and organizations, news, and special events such as the Miss Chinatown pageants. (1 box, plus newspaper issues)
Biographical / Historical
Gene L. Lee, military veteran, entrepreneur, and publisher, was born on October 5, 1926, in Canton, part of China's Guangdong province. While only a young boy, Lee's father left their village of Toisan and traveled to Canada. Lee's mother passed away soon thereafter and Lee was raised by his sister with financial assistance provided by their father in Canada. Lee rarely spoke of his early childhood, for it was certainly marked by upheaval and uncertainty.
Lee did, however, travel in a month-long journey to the United States in 1949. His family was instrumental in aiding his travels: his father helped pay for the ship voyage, uncles and cousins joined Lee, and he ultimately lived with his sister and her husband in Houston, Texas. Soon after arriving in Texas, Lee was drafted into the United States Army and was assigned to occupation duty in Germany. Lee fondly remembered his service in the military as a time in which he met people of great diversity and was exposed to a host of disciplines including classes on typing, mathematics, and history. These formative experiences reflected Lee's life-long ambition to learn as much as possible through self-education.
While in Germany Lee met his future wife, Hedy. Following a courtship of only six weeks, Gene and Hedy married. The couple knew very little English and used a pocket dictionary to assist their communication. The Lees lived for two years in Germany while Gene completed his military service.
The couple returned to Houston and Lee began working in at his uncle's grocery. Gene and Hedy, though, soon purchased their own market and, throughout the 1960s, turned it into a successful business. Lee exhibited a strong work-ethic and labored seven days a week. Gene's Food Market, located at 3404 Leeland, was a family enterprise; all five of the Lee children worked in the store.
In 1970 Lee opened Lee Printing Company in Houston. He had long expressed an interest in the printing business, took community college courses on the subject, and sought advice from some of Houston's existing printers. Lee Printing provided both English and Chinese printing services and even sold office supplies to other businesses.
The printing industry directed the already successful Lee toward publishing his own newspaper. In 1976, he introduced the region's first Chinese/English newspaper, the Southwest Chinese Journal. Similar to his success in the grocery and printing business, Lee's positive influence was easily seen in the printing industry. One of his employees, Wea Lee (no relation), a Lamar University graduate, later founded the Southern News Group, which publishes multiple Chinese-language papers.
Lee retired from his prosperous businesses in 1994 and handed the daily operations to his son, Sam. Gene Lee, in addition to being a successful entrepreneur and businessman was also an avid reader and dedicated to self-education. He immersed himself in classical Chinese literature, history, and poetry. A connoisseur of Chinese music, Lee played violin with a Cantonese opera group.
Gene Lee passed away on October 24, 2010, and was survived by his wife, Hedy, their five children, nine grandchildren, and one great-grandaughter.
Scope and Contents
Newspaper issues of the Southwest Chinese Journal (cataloged separately), photographs submitted to the newspaper for publication purposes and a small amount of correspondence regarding the Lee Printing Company of Houston, Texas, owned by Gene and Hedy Lee. The newspapers and photographs reflect Chinese culture in Houston during the 1970s and 1980s, including family life, business activities, cultural arts and organizations, news, and special events such as the Miss Chinatown contests. The bulk of the materials are comprised of these photographs, many of which taken by photographer Alvin Wong Gee. Gene's Food Market materials include wholesale grocery receipts and two interior photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated by Gene & Hedy Lee, 2010. Audio reels donated 2017 by Hedy Lee.
Arrangement
Newspapers are cataloged separately in the Fondren Library catalog. They are available in the Woodson Research Center and in the Asian Studies Alcove, Fondren Library 1st floor.
Photographs are arranged by the original subject groupings provided by Gene and Hedy Lee.
Separated Materials
Newspaper issues of the Southwest Chinese Journal have been cataloged separately and are available in the Fondren Library's Asian Studies Alcove (1st floor) and in the Woodson Research Center. Years present in the run of newspapers are 1976-1978, 1979 is missing, 1980-1985.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Chinese Americans; Asians -- America -- History; Chinese Americans--Cultural assimilation; Asian Americans; Journalism
Document Types
receipts (financial records); clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; photographs; black-and-white photographs; newspapers
Places
Texas--Houston
Subjects (Persons)
Lee, Hedy, Mrs.
- Series I: Photographs, 1976-1985; 114645
  - Business locations, awards, and professional portraits, 114647 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Identified individuals include Young Il Lee, Alvin Gee (photographer), William Der Bing (NASA Public Information Specialist), Deborah Young Lim (Interior Design), Hardy J. Lee (police), Dr. Rose Tang, Sue-Hwa Loo (biologist), Russell David Yang, Luois Chow (pharmacist), Lily Yeo (police), Roberta T.S. Lee (M.D.), Kwun Kay Szeto (owner of Barbecue Shop), Dr. James Tsao (lecturer), June Dove Leong (jeweler?), Dr. James Tang (M.D.), Patrick Cheng (China Restaurant), Steve and Annie Tsui (Steve's Food market No. 2) and Chris Lee (Deputy Sheriff). Businesses pictured include Diho Market, Yank Sing Chinese 7 American restaurant, Golden Palace restaurant, Chuen Sun Import Export, You Name It Antiques Plants & Gifts. Professions represented (by unidentified individuals) include restauranteurs, bankers, radio dj's, students, and more.
  - Chinese cultural arts, 114648 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Featured art forms include music, dance, dress, artifacts / objects, martial arts, dragon costumes, dishes, exhibits. People featured include Li Cunxin of the Houston ballet, Peter Lin and others of the Chinese Christian Art Crusade, Tom Ng with guitar and others.
  - Chinese in the news (local), 114649 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Many of these photos feature Chinese in Houston appearing with Mayor Kathy Whitmire at political events.
  - Chinese in the news (national), 114650 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Chinese campaigning for democratic candidates in U.S.; Bette Bao Lord (author of novel, Spring Moon); photographer Alvin Gee with celebrities at Inc. Magazine's 500 Fastest Growing Companies event in Houston, May 1984.
  - Chinese organizations, 114651 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes images of the Sharpstown Senior High Chinese Cultural Club, Texas Buddhist Association, Chinese American Citizens Alliance (with Councilman Frank Mancuso and event emcee Ping Yang Chou), University of Houston Chinese Student Association, and the YMCA Indochinese Refugee Program.
  - Family banquets and receptions, 114667 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Color snapshots of groups in restaurants or other banquet facilities, or at other family and friend celebrations and events. Not all images are indentified. Some of the identified names include Bernard Go, Edward Woo and family, Robert Foo Lee, Mr. and Mrs. Bill Woo, Major James McConn, Dorothy Toy (Chan) at the Great Wall, Terry Chang, Sherman Tiym Albert Lee, Henry Lee and Larry Y. Woo.
  - Individuals and groups (1 of 2), 114652 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Not all photographs are identified. Names appearing on the identified photographs include Mrs. Margaret Seito Wong, Mrs. H. Wong, Ton and Mamie Yee, Dr. Hwa Jer Tsai, Cindy Li, Karen M. Lee, Frances Wong, Pauline Wong, Pauline Hou Chan, Allen Gau, Betty Lee, C.C. Huang, K.C. Chen, F.C. Lin, S.C. Huang, S.T. Hsu, C.H. Chen, W.T. Hsu, Deanna and Cameron, Jennifer Liu, Natalie Hsu, Dr. ned Hwang and Mr. San Hwang, Dr. James Tong, Liang Chi, Daniel H.L. Chang, David Ng, Darlene Chan, Jane E. Gee, Congresswoman Lera Thomas, Father Luis Chia, Dr. Jue Kang, Dr. Baldwin H. Tom, Esther Lee Yao, Danny Lee, Jiua Lu, Mary Toy, Tom Ng, Frank SUng, Tarzan Huang, Ting Sun, Lap Wong,Martha Wong, Simone Gee, Frank O. Mancuso, Consul General Shan-Chung Lee, Bobby T. Lo, Michelle Fang, Carol Eng, Donna Wong, Philip Cheung, Father Francies X. Chang.
  - Individuals and groups (2 of 2), 114668 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Not all photographs are identified. Names appearing on the identified photographs include Mayor Jim McConn, Geneva Kirk Brooks, Mr. and Mrs. Chuang Li Huang, Bill Woo, Lewis Yee, Bill Quan, Patrick P.C. Chang, Lee Chia, Kim Gee, Dr. Roland C.K. Ng, Dr. Benning Tan Lu, Mr. and Mrs. Peter Chin, Jeff Yao, Ho family, Ting Sun, Suzanne See, Amy Sit, Rev. and Mrs. Wang, Helen Liu, Dr. Joyce Fan, Chin family, Minister Mo-Sung-nien, Consul general Chuan-li Huang, Mr. and Mrs. Eo Hong, Pastor David Chan, Mr. and Mrs. Kellogg Wong (architect), Dr. Beng Ho, Herbert King, Shen Gee Foy, Dr. Hong Sit, Dr. Katherine Hsu, actress Debra Paget Kung, Gordon Gee, Robert and Susan Dawn, Howard Fong, Marilyn Hsu, Dr. Tzu C. Lu, William Simm, Howard Shunon Tsoi, Chan-Huie Yang with violinist Cho-Liang Lin, Daniel and Myra Chang, ted Wu,Mr. and Mrs. Harry Ng, Mary Ann Wong, Mr. Lubowsky.
  - Mrs. June Dove Leong, 114653 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Portraits of Mrs. Leong as well as family photographs such as the wedding of her daughter.
  - Miss. Chinatown contest, 114654 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Color and black and white snapshots of the Miss Chinatown contest events as well portraits of the contestants. Names include Shirley Ng, Virginia Chang, Clara Chou, Elizabeth Jee, Ellen Gee, Bella Truong, Muoy Kuon, Suzette Hong, Wai Man Ip, Ying Mai Wu, Yvonne Lai. Not all images are identified.
  - Press release photographs, 114655 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Press releases sent in to the Southwest Chinese Journal for publication, covering general event topics in Houston such as performances coming up at Astroworld.
  - Scholarship winners, 114656 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - SWCJ Salutes, 114657 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sports, events, tournaments, 114658 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Weddings, 114659 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    These are generally color snapshots of the bride and groom in the wedding ceremony location, with some additional photographs of family posing with the couple. Names which appear include Mr. and Mrs. Kenneth Eng, Doris and Lonnie Liu, Mr. and Mrs. Ben Liu, Mr. and Mrs. Jimmy Wong, Hubert and Betsy Cheung, Mr. and Mrs. Russell Wong, Irene and Franc Lee, Mr. and Mrs. Daniel Chee, Mr. and Mrs. Bill Ong.
  - Who's Who in Houston, 114660 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series II: Lee Printing Company correspondence and staff photographs, 1985-2010, 114646
  - Lee Printing Company correspondence and staff photographs, 1985-2010, 114661 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series III: Newsclippings, 1977-1980, 114662
  - Newsclippings on Chinese in Houston, 114663 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Clippings from the Houston Chronicle, Houston Post and Southwest Chinese Journal regarding Chinese in Houston and President Carter's foreign relations efforts with China.
- Series IV: Gene's Food Market receipts and photographs, 1962-1969, 114664
  - Gene's Food Market receipts, 1968-1969, 114665 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Receipts for goods delivered to Gene's Food Market from companies such as Hogan-Allnoch Co., Schott's Sunbeam Bread, Borden's, Mrs. Bairds, Lone Star Beer, Grocers' Supply Company, Rainbow Baking Co., E.L. Sauer & Sons Sausage and Bacon, Emmett's Seafood and others.
  - Gene's Food market interior photographs, 1958, 114666 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Featuring Gene and Hedy Lee in the market, as well as staff member Robert Holiday and an undientified staff member. Robert Holiday is also noted and photographed here as having worked with the Lee family at the Lee Printing Company in the 1970s.
- Series V: Documents
  - "Save and Borrow: The Texas Lee Federal Credit" booklet (in Chinese) (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series VI: Audio correspondence reels, 1960s
  - Audio correspondence reels between Gene Lee in Houston and his brother in Canada, 1960s (Box 2, Box 3)